Guide to the W. H. Pegram Papers, 1876 - 1928 UA.29.02.0058
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
W. H. Pegram papers
1876 - 1928
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pegram, W. H. (William Howell), 1846-1928
UA.29.02.0058
1.75 Linear Feet
William Howell Pegram (1846-1928) was a student, professor, and administrator at Trinity College (N.C.). He moved with the school from Randolph County to Durham County (N.C.), and remained active as Trinity College evolved into Duke University. The W.H. Pegram Papers include correspondence, notebooks, writings, clippings, and other material. His relationship with Braxton Craven, both professionally and personally, is detailed. Among the subjects in the collection are Pegram's main academic interest, chemistry, and the administration of Trinity College in both Randolph and Durham counties. English.
1700 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The W. H. Pegram Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1978.
Biographical Note
William Howell Pegram was born August 18, 1846, in Harnett County, North Carolina. He served as a Confederate soldier during the Civil War. Following the war, he returned to his parents' farm and taught in the small schools of Harnett County. In 1869, he began college at Trinity College in Randolph County. He was regarded as an excellent student and worked closely with Braxton Craven, the president of Trinity College.
Pegram graduated in 1873, and beginning that fall, he began working as a tutor of Natural Science at Trinity. He became a full professor the following year. He would eventually serve as a professor of chemistry, astronomy, geology, and even English during his career, although chemistry was his passion. When Craven died in 1882, Pegram became chairman of the faculty, and from 1883 to 1910, he served as Secretary of the faculty. He was honored with an L.L.D. degree from Trinity in 1917, and made Professor Emeritus of Chemistry in 1919. He remained active with the school and the Department of Chemistry until his death, always staying interested in the students and faculty of his school. Pegram was one of very few faculty members to work with the school in all its phases, from its beginnings in Randolph County, to its move to Durham County, to its growth and change into Duke University in 1924. He was known as "The Grand Old Man of Duke University" by many of his students.
In 1875, Pegram married Braxton Craven's daughtor, Emma L. Craven. They had five children, all of whom attended Trinity: Annie M. Pegram, George B. Pegram, Irene C. Pegram, J. Edward Pegram, and William H. Pegram, Jr. William H. Pegram, Sr. passed away on April 30, 1928, ending a 55-year career with Duke University and Trinity College. He is buried at "Old Trinity," in Randolph County, near the grave of Braxton Craven.
Collection Overview
The W. H. Pegram Collection includes correspondence, notebooks, writings, clippings, and other material related to Pegram's career at Trinity College and later Duke University. The first series, Personal, is a brief series containing clippings and other material regarding Pegram's career and his death in 1928. The second series Correspondence, contains letters to and from Pegram, mainly regarding administrative issues at Trinity College. There are also some letters of thanks from former students. This series is arranged chronologically. The third series is Notebooks, and contains notebooks used by Pegram for a variety of purposes: to record the attendance and grades of his students, to prepare Sunday school lessons, to work on chemistry problems, and to write essays. The notebooks are arranged by title or subject, when available, then date. The fourth series, Writings, contains several essays prepared by Pegram, as well as shorter pieces. This series is also organized by title, when available, and then date. The last series, Trinity College, contains a variety of materials related to the history of the school. These materials are not all directly related to Pegram, but they provide a historical context for his other materials. It contains clippings, articles, financial papers, and print materials about the school. These papers are organized alphabetically.
Related Material
Craven (Braxton) Papers, 1839-1882
Duke University Archives
Kilgo (John C.) Records and Papers, 1888-1970 (bulk 1894-1920)
Duke University Archives
Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) Collection, 1836-1990
Duke University Archives
Craven-Pegram Family Papers, 1785-1966
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Notebooks; Craven, B. (Braxton), 1822-1882; Craven family; Pegram, W. H. (William Howell), 1846-1928; Pegram, W. H. (William Howell), 1846-1928; Pegram family; Duke University. Department of Chemistry; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) -- Faculty; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.); Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- History; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Faculty; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.); Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) -- History
- Personal, 1885-1928
  - Clippings - Career, 1885-1921, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memorial, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1882-1928
  - 1882 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1883 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1884 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1885-1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1890-1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1894-1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1901-1903 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1910-1916 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1920 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1923-1925 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1926-1928 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Notebooks, 1873-1916
  - "The Advancement of Chemistry in the Schools of North Carolina," [undated] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Early History of Trinity College," [undated] (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - "Education and Religion," [undated] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Electrochemistry Report, circa 1906 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Examination and Grade Book, circa 1899-1905 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Grade Book, September 1916 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Grade Book and Other Notes, [undated] (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Grade Book and Roll of Classes, 1873-1883 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "How to Prepare and Teach the Sunday School Lesson," [undated] (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Notes on Chemistry and Grade Book, [undated] (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Radio Activity": Faculty Lecture, circa 1905 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Religious Writings, [undated, includes loose papers] (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Sketches and Skeletons and Sermons," [undated] (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "The Study of Nature," [undated] (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 1882-1883 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Circa 1891 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - 1901 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - [Undated] (Box 3, Folder 32-37)
- Writings, 1884-1927
  - "The Development of the Department of Physics at Duke University," [undated] (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Frank C. Robbins, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - "A Sketch of Randolph County," 1884 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - W. F. Gill, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - "Who Founded Trinity College?" August 1926 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - [Undated] (Box 3, Folder 43-44)
- Trinity College, 1876-1926
  - Article Transcripts, 1926, [undated] (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Braxton Craven Medal Rules, [undated] (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - By-Laws, Trinity College Alumnae Association, [undated] (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Clippings, 1886-1916, [undated] (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Clippings - Braxton Craven, 1882-1899 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Dept. of Chemistry Course Descriptions, June 1910 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Financial Papers, 1876-1915 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Inn Plot drawn by W. H. Pegram, Jr., March 2, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, December 8-13, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Printed Material
    - 1884-1894 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - 1895-1906 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - 1907-1910 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - 1911-1919 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - 1920-1924, [undated] (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Reunion - Class of 1873, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Reunion - Class of 1873, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 60)